Guide to the Cornell University Military Science and ROTC Records, 1890-2002.
Cornell University Military Science and ROTC Records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University Military Science and ROTC Records, 1890-2002.
33-2-4134
Cornell University. ROTC
3.5 c.ft.
Reports, photographs, research material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes reports, meeting minutes, subject files and photographs pertaining to the Cornell ROTC program.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes reports, meeting minutes, subject files and photographs pertaining to the Cornell ROTC program and Cornellians who served in the military. Many materials relating to the service of Floyd R. Newman. Letters from soldiers home, many from World War I. Also a 1958 film from The Big Picture series showcasing Cornell.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Cornell University -- Students.; Newman, Floyd R. (Floyd Roy), 1890-1990; United States Army.; United States. Army Reserve Officers' Training Corps.
Subjects:
Military education.; Aeronautics, Military -- New York (State) -- Ithaca; World War, 1914-1918.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 9 - During student's lifetime individual transcripts restricted to permission of student and ROTC office.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Administrative Documents and Miscellany
  - Barton Hall, 1913-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - President White's Letter - copy, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Facts About the ROTC Program, 1950s-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unit History, no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Land Grant Colleges - Circulars, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Change to General Military Science Curriculum, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Change to General Military Science Curriculum, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ROTC Curriculum, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - University Committees on Military Curricula and Requirements for Graduation, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - University Committees on Military Curricula and Requirements for Graduation, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arts and Sciences Credit Project, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - University ROTC Relationship Committee, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University ROTC Relationship Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University ROTC Relationship Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - University ROTC Relationship Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - University ROTC Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Senate Actions, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Enrollment Graphs, 1961-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cross Enrollment, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Army Specialized Training Program - WWII, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cornell Statistics - WWI - War Memorial, no date (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Establishment of ROTC Flight Training, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - New York State Medical College - ROTC, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Korea and Vietnam Casualties, no date (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Brigadier General R. Dean Tice Visit, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1885-1887 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1890-1896 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1917, 1925-1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Cadet Rosters, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cadet Handbook, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1916-1929 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual Reports, 1979-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Report of Presidential Commission on Military Training, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Presidential Review, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - ROTC Debate, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Senate Debate on ROTC, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Commissioning, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Commissioning, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Commissioning, 1963-1964, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Programs - Commissioning Ceremonies and Awards Ceremonies, 1990-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Presidential Commission, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Pledging Scabbard and Blade, 1949-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters - "Barton Banner" and "The Recoil", 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1980s-2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Papers by Students about ROTC, 1980s and 1990s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Bequest - Colonel Wortham, 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - War Maps, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - WWI Appreciation Booklet from Simon Long's Sons, Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania and Postcard to the "Heroes of Desert Storm" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Film from The Big Picture series showcasing Cornell, 1958; CD-2082 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Also a February 1958 article from the ALumni News about the filming.
  - Postcards and guide of Trier, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Postcards and guides of France, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Postcards and guide of Coblenz, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Guides and Maps of Rhineland, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - USS Leviathan pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Infantry and field service regulations, 1911, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 10 points for cadet battalion success (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - France ally pamphlets, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - WWI newspaper clippings, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Excelsior Battalion budgets, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cornell Annual Horse Show program, May 12, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Upper Alumni Field, featuring Field Artillery R.O.T.C, Polo Club, and Cayuga Valley Riding and Hunt Club.
  - Eleventh Annual Cornell R.O.T.C. Horse Show and Gymkana, May 2, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Stars and Stripes newspaper, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - ROTC certificate, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Binder of committee notes, 1960s (Box 8)
  - Cornell Veteran and Military Community alumni reunion weekend materials, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Army Specialized Training Program - Academic Transcripts - (A-CON) - During student's lifetime individual transcripts restricted to permission of student and ROTC office., 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Robert Stack certificate "Ordre National de la Legion D'honneur", 1951-11-01 (Folder 1)
  - Part of a German military map, Undated (Folder 1)
- Series II. Alumni Materials
  - Past Professors of Military Science (PMS), 1868-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Joseph Whittlesey (1868-1870), George Bell (1892-1895) - PMS, 1868-1895 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Major Arnold (1870-1873), James Burbank (1877-1883) - PMS, 1870-1883 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ervin Phillips (1908-1911), Henry Bull (1913-1915) - PMS, 1908-1915 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - John J. Fulmer (1932-1937), Waldo Potter (1937-1940), G. S. Smith (1951-1954) - PMS, 1932-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Richard Comstock (1954-1957), William Allen (1957-1960) - PMS, 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Charles Blumenfeld (1960-1962), Miller (1962-1965) - PMS, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Martin Waters (1965-1968), Claude Bailey (1968-1972) - PMS, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Robert Chamberlain (1972-1975), Gerard Luisi (1975) - PMS (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Robert D'Entremont, Buchwald (1985-1988) - PMS, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Edward Tinkham - Class of 1912, 1928-1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Allan Eggers - Class of 1919, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Robert Stack - Class of 1923, 1965-1990 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Matt Urban - Class of 1941, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Arthur Conklin - Class of 1894, Howard Wortham - Class of 1914, 1934-1954 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Jess Creech - Class of 1920, John Donaldson - Class of 1921, George Pfann - Class of 1924, no date (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bruce Clarke - Class of 1927, Derrill Daniel - Class of 1933, George Hologhwost - Class of 1937, 1951-1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Robert Taber - Class of 1938, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Harold Parker - Class of 1938, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - F.R. Newman, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - F.R. Newman - Photos - Wortham Museum Barton Hall uniform exhibit dedication, 1963-1964, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - F.R. Newman - Shanghai Story, 1912-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Events and Memorable Experiences by F.R. Newman, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - FR Newman papers, 1916-1922 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Certificates: "Rangers" certificate of appreciation 1984, Selden Allis, William Bradley (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - William Bradley papers, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Torn letters to Lucius Hopwood (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Letters from Lucius Hopwood to wife and daughter, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Letters to Audentia Hopwood, 1921-1935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Letters to Lucius Hopwood, 1914-1918 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Hopwood miscellany (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Lucius Hopwood wallet and pocket dictionary (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Victor Reese, Ralph Hall poem (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - John W. Mack, College of Military Science certificate - rank of Captain in Corps of Cornell Cadets, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Photo of Joseph Sydney Barr's War Alumnus proclamation, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Materials relating to the Barton Hall World War Two Remembrance Garden Dedication, 2017; EStorage - A171-07-001
    Includes material on Cornellians Frederick Johnson, Matt Urban, Rodney Gould, and Raymond Thorpe.
- Series III. Photographs and slides
  - Photographs, 1890-2002 (Box 4)
    Multiple wars, WW1, Newman material, canons, etc..
  - Photo album pages, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ranger challenge, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photograph, SVC 9 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - WWI Train photo (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Howard Evans badges (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Vietnam slides, 1967-1968, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photo album, 1990s (Box 8)
  - Photograph scrapbook album, 1950s (Box 5)
  - Photograph scrapbook album (Box 6)
  - Photograph scrapbook album (Box 7)
  - Photographs of FR Newman certificate (Box 7)
  - Photographs of graduating classes, 1917-1918 (Box 7)
  - Lehigh valley reserve officers, Military ball, 1950-02-26 (Box 7)
  - ROTC duty with W.B. Larew, 1933-1938 (Box 7)
  - Photograph of O.C.C. #17, Camp Hood, Texas, 1943-02-11 (Box 7)
  - Barton Hall truck show photograph, 1920's (Folder 1)
  - Group photograph of Cornell Military Department, 1919-05-20 (Folder 1)
  - Photograph of Cornell University annual inspection - Reserve Officers Training Corps, Spring 1917 (Folder 1)
  - Photograph of 644 A, Fort Lewis Washington (Folder 2)
  - Photograph of officers and cadets, with Capt. Pangborn Parsons and commanding officer (Folder 2)